RYAN BUTLER

Claremont, CA | 425.765.4451 | rmbutler@outlook.com | github.com/RyanButler53

SOFTWARE DEVELOPER

I am a motivated computer science major focused on machine learning and utilizing specialized data structures to achieve highly performant code. I have worked extensively with computational modeling and designing specific data structures to handle the interfaces required for efficiently simulating complex systems. Comfortable using matplotlib to visualize large scale datasets. I manage my own project roadmaps and development timelines. I am also experienced at tutoring and collaborating with others to more deeply understand computer science concepts.

EDUCATION

Harvey Mudd College Expected May 2024

Bachelor of Science, BS, Computer Science, Minor in Music Performance | GPA 3.632.

Dean's List: Spring 2021 | Fall 2021 | Spring 2022 | Fall 2022 | Spring 2023.

Relevant Coursework: Principles of Computer Science | Data Structures and Program Development | Computing for Insight | Discrete Mathematics | Linear Algebra | Probability and Statistics | Differential Equations | Algorithms Machine Learning (Reinforcement Learning) | Computer Systems.

SKILLS

Programming Languages: C++ | Python | C | Java | Shell | R | Prolog | Racket.

Software and Libraries: Github | LLDB/GDB | Markdown | Matplotlib | Pandas | NumPy | Valgrind | LaTeX | Seaborn.

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Harvey Mudd College, Research Intern

June 2022 - Present

- Furthered multiple Reinforcement Learning (RL) projects in the Mini Atari environment.
- Explored different ways of reusing data to decrease interactions with the environment.
- Optimized a from-scratch decision tree codebase to run 80x faster, allowing for scalable experimentation.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Harvey Mudd College, Grader/Tutor

September 2021 - Present

- Introduction to CS | Computing for Inquiry | Data Structures | Algorithms.
- Explained course concepts and answered homework questions for hundreds of students.

PERSONAL PROJECTS

Modeled the ranking system of a popular mobile game (C++ | Shell | Python)

March 2023

- Used an Object-Oriented approach to create an efficient ranking system model.
- Experimentally optimized system parameters to minimize repetitive gameplay.
- Wrote a shell script to automate experiments.
- Visualized multiple trials of data in Python's Matplotlib.
- Documented source code: https://github.com/RyanButler53/PathOfLegends.

Created a model of an Elo-based ranking system (C++ | Python)

January 2022 - August 2022

- Modeled the system by using a specialized Random BST along with OOP.
- Wrote a script to graph results in Python's Matplotlib.
- Documented source code: https://github.com/RyanButler53/CRLadder2.1.

Implemented C++ class templates of various interesting and unusual data structures

Ongoing since May 2023

- Splay Tree: Implements map interface with no extra overhead in nodes and offers an iterator.
- Cuckoo-HashMap/HashSet: Implements set and map interface with constant time worst case lookup.
- Interval Tree: Allows for efficient querying of intervals that intersect a given point.
- Quack: Implements the queue interface 10-20x faster than the std::queue library.
- Minqueue: Implements the queue interface plus constant time minimum lookup.
- Skip List (Ongoing): Working on a probabilistic alternative to a self-balancing binary search tree